Hello everyone, the third edition of voice
Всім привіт третій випуск голосових
messages. And today we're going to talk about
повідомлень І сьогодні ми поговоримо про
why developers are afraid to create
те чому розробники бояться створювати
new files, not even new files, new
нові файли навіть не нові файли нові
abstractions, and I'll tell you a few stories.
абстракції і я розповім декілька історій
When I observed this, it was just a
Коли я це спостерігав і це Прям
strange, strange phenomenon that I
дивний-дивний такий феномен який я
saw. I even added a slide to my
побачив я навіть додав слайд в свою
presentation at Dow Day, but unfortunately I didn't have time to
презентацію на Dow Day але на жаль не
do it. Well, I didn't have enough time
встиг зробити Ну не було достатньо часу
to talk about this phenomenon in detail.
в мене щоб розповісти в деталях про цей
So let's go through it now.
феномен от давайте зараз пройдемо ось по
Developers often work according to a
ньому е розробники часто працюють по
template and when there are certain abstractions in the project.
шаблону і коли є в проекті певні
They are often afraid to create some
абстракції Вони часто бояться створити
new abstractions. Experienced
нові якісь абстракції досвідчені
developers do this, but developers
розробники роблять це але розробники в
who don't have enough experience often
яких недостатньо досвіду Вони часто
just try to reuse
просто намагаються перевикористати
existing abstractions. They either
існуючі абстракції і вони або
use existing files and add
використовують існуючі файли і додають в
content to them. This is the first option. The second
них е контент це перший варіант Другий
option is if they have some pattern where
варіант якщо у них є якийсь паттерн де
they need to copy files and create by
їм треба копіювати файли і створювати по
analogy, then they don't copy files. That is,
аналогії то не копіюють файли тобто
developers either copy files with an existing
розробники або копіюють файли з існуючою
structure or use files
структурою або використовують файли в
that already have a certain structure and new
яких вже є певна структура і нові
abstractions are very rarely added. And now
абстракції дуже рідко додаються І зараз
I'm here.  I'll tell you a few
я от розповім декілька
stories. The first story is about
історій перша історія - це про
testing. We once had a
тестування у нас колись там веіле був
project there. Well, there are many projects. We have a
проект Ну багато проектів у нас є
standard approach. There is a set of tests there. We
стандартний підхід є набір там тестів ми
write unit tests for the backend. For example, there
пишемо ціюнітести для бекенду наприклад
is a test Factory. This is an abstraction
і є tтеest Factory - це така абстракція
that allows you to create
яка дозволяє створити
test users there. I don't know
там тестових юзерів тестові там не знаю
what data materials there are. Or something else. Well,
якісь дані матеріали склади ще щось ну в
depending on the system, and that is,
залежності від системи та тобто за
using the test factory, we can
допомогою тестфкторі ми можемо
create an environment. We also have,
засстапити оточення і Також у нас є
for example, we use tea as a
Наприклад ми використовуємо чаї як
library for asters. Here we
бібліотеку для асртів і тут в нас
need to write our own art
виникає необхідність написати свій арт
that checks the calendar date. And this
який перевіряє календарну дату і цей
assr is called Ass Date. And I
assр там Ass Date називається і я
look at the tests and I see that it is written there. Test
дивлюсь тести і я бачу написано там Test
Factory is a bit dated and Data is passed.
Factory крапas datate і передається Data
Because we use Test Factory everywhere in the tests.
тому що у нас усюди по тестам
This Test Factory object is available. And where can we add
цей об'єкт Test Factory і куди ж додати
this asord Date method if not in the existing
цей метод asord Date як не в існуючий
Test Factory class, although the responsibility of the
клас Test Factory хоча відповідальність
abstraction class is completely different. It
класа ції абстракції зовсім в іншому і
was necessary to simply create a
треба було просто створити насправді
new abstraction, a new module in which
нову абстракцію новий модуль в який
to place one method there or one
помістити Да один метод там чи один одну
assort Date function. And actually  everything but
функцію assort Date І власне все але
developers for some reason don't do this
розробники цього чомусь не роблять
and the first thing that comes to mind that they
і і перше що на думку приходить що вони
don't do this is because it is necessary
не роблять це це тому що це треба
to create a new file But as I see new
створити новий файл Але як я бачу нові
files are created very often and when we
файли створюються дуже часто і коли ми
write in React when we write backend
пишемо на реакті коли ми пишемо backend
We create a lot of new files and
Ми створюємо дуже багато нових файлів і
it is rather not a question of creating a new
це скоріше не питання створення нового
file But the question of creating a new
файлу А питання створення нової
abstraction that was not there and here we need to
абстракції якої не було і тут треба
think about how to do it correctly And this is
подумати як же його зробити правильно А
additional effort that often the developer is
це додаткові зусилля які часто розробник
not always ready to accept
не завжди розробник готовий в прийняти
In addition, a more experienced developer
крім того більш досвідчений розробник
understands the consequences of such a decision
розуміє наслідки наслідки такого рішення
to place some abstraction there in the test
помістити там якийсь асрт в теest
factor and a less experienced one may not yet
factкторі а менш досвідчений може ще не
understand that is why such a situation arises
розуміти тому виникає така ситуація
In fact, there is such a classic anti-pattern
насправді є такий класичний антипатерн
called got Object when
який називається got Object коли Просто
We simply throw too much responsibility into some one class,
ми в якийсь один клас закидаємо занадто
too
багато відповідальності занадто багато
many things that are not connected by
багато речей які між собою не поєднані
some idea For example, I observed
якоюсь ідеєю наприклад я спостерігав
when there are too many utilities thrown into the base class of services
коли там в базовий клас сервісів
because
накидають забагато утиліт тому що
instead of creating date utils there
замість того щоб створити там date utils
there are some File utils and so on Session
там якись File utils і так далі Session
utils or there Session Store all this is just so that
utils чи там Session Store все це просто
it is available to all children
щоб воно було доступно всім дочірнім
classes are simply thrown into the main
класам просто накидається В основний
base class, as a result, this base
базовий клас в результаті цей базовий
class is transformed into such a got Object,
клас перетворюється в такий в got Object
which is an anti-pattern, in principle, the second
що є антипатерном в принципі друга
story is also with webilab and we had to
історія теж з webilab і нам треба було
develop a webab presentation system like
розробити webab таку систему презентацій
PowerPoint, that is, you have different
по типу PowerPoint тобто У вас є різні
objects, slides, you can move them on these slides,
об'єкти слайди ви на цих слайдах можете
rotate them, move them, add them,
рухати їх крутити переміщати додавати
delete them. Well, in fact, to create slides
видаляти Ну і по суті створювати слайди
on the web, I created a basic proof of
в вебі я створив базовий такий proof of
concept in which it was on React, in
Concept в якому це було на реакті в
which I described what data structure it
якому я описав яку структуру даних яка в
will be serialized into, in fact, the
яку буде серіалізуватися власне ее сам
slide itself described some basic primitives,
слайд описав е якісь базові примітиви
there is a widget and a widget, which has some
там віджет і вджет в якого є там якісь
parameters, where it is located, how it is
параметри де він знаходиться як
rotated, and so on, there are some
повернутий і так далі якісь є
properties in it or a configuration file for each
проertiesies в нього чи кофіг у кожного
widget, and I wrote
віджета і написав
a couple of standard widgets there, conditionally there is a
пару там стандартних віджетів умовно там
circle, a square, or a rectangle, text, and
коло квадрат чи там прямокутник текст і
so on, so that you could make basic
так далі щоб можна було робити базові
presentations, and it was basically such a
презентації і це в принципі був такий
small file, I don't remember, there were maybe a
невеличкий файлік я не пам'ятаю там може
hundred lines of code there, and  I gave the
на на сотню строк коду і я віддав
developers I say look at this proof of
розробникав кажу дивіться от proof of
concept like this can you
Concept такий типу от можна це
implement it That is, it's not some
реалізувати Тобто це не є якоюсь там
super super No well that is, it's a task that
супер супер Не ну тобто це задача яка
will require time but it can all be done
вимагатиме часу але це все можна зробити
because that's it we can already do
тому що от воно ми можемо вже робити
slides now and we just need to finish
зараз слайди і нам треба просто доробити
this widget system and if we build an
цю систему віджетів і якби побудувати
infrastructure around this that Of course
інфраструктуру навтоколо цього що Звісно
there is more than one month of work but it's real
там не один місяць роботи але це реально
and after six months I come to the project and
і через півроку я приходжу на проект і
look at this widget system and
дивлюсь на на оцю систему віджетів і
see that there is a file in which there are 5,000 lines of
бачу що є файл в якому там 5 000 строк
code and all the widgets all all there are some
коду і всі віджети все всі там якісь
additional things related to from all in
додаткові речі пов'язані з від все в
one file I look at it like this and well
одному файлі я такий дивлюсь на це і ну
I understand well it's impossible to support
я розумію ну це ж неможливо супортити
because it's all mixed up besides these
тому що воно все перемішано крім того
eyes it's clear that the widgets have grown in
оці зрозуміло що віджети розрослися в
them more responsibility has been
них стало більше відповідальності
added some additional subsystems on the
додалися якісь підсистеми додаткові на
slides there some synchronization Well that's all and
слайдах там якась синхронізація Ну все і
I say And what are you doing and the
я кажу А що ви так От так От робите і
answer was Well it's you it's you
відповідь була Ну це ж ти це ж ти так
showed us so did Well I think Well I  I
нам показав зробив Ну я думаю Ну я ж
showed when there were 100 lines of code and
показав коли там було 100 строк коду а
not 5,000, it is clear that when it grows,
не 5 000 зрозуміло що коли вона зростає
new responsibilities appear for us.
у нас з'являються нові
Well, we see that we have to
відповідальності Ну ми бачимо ми маємо
allocate new abstractions. So this is a similar
виділяти нові абстракції От і це схожа
situation when developers simply see
ситуація коли просто розробники бачать
some pattern that it is structured in a
якийсь патерн що воно структуровано в
certain way, yes, because there
певним чином да тому що там
was a structure and they start to simply add, add
структура була і вони починають просто
and add something to the
додавати додавати і додавати щось в
existing structure and are afraid to create
існуючу структуру і бояться створити
new abstractions, and they suffer from this.
нові абстракції при тому від цього вони
They understand how
страждають вони розуміють як це
inefficient it is, how inconvenient it is, and in fact, it seems to
неефективно як це там незручно і вони от
me that they even
насправді мені здається навіть самі
initiated this review themselves because they say, "
ініціювали це рев'ю тому що кажуть Щось
They can't do something, they can't take off, it's
вони не можуть Щось вони не взлітає за
already difficult, it turns out interesting." But how do
це вже складно виходить цікаво Да як от
developers follow the existing structure, it's
розробники слідують існуючій структурі
just different? The third story, in principle, I
просто інше третя історія в принципі я
already told in the last issue of
вже розповів в минулому випуску
voice messages about builders, that is, for
голосових повідомлень про білдери тобто
example, if you have some
Наприклад якщо у вас є якась
low-level abstraction there, GRD, and you
низькорівнева абстракція там ГРД І у вас
have a declarative config for this grid,
є конфіг декларативний для цього гріда
then often everyone just describes it
то часто всі просто його Так і описують
in all places of the project. Although it was possible to
в усіх місцях проекту Хоча можна було
take it higher, it turns out interesting.
взяти зробити більш високо вневу
abstraction or some facade that would
абстракцію або якийсь фасад який
allow more convenient and
дозволив би більш більш зручно і в
project-specific way to
специфічний для проекта спосіб
configure there to build this GRD and
конфігурувати там будувати цей ГРД і
accordingly have these builders makes sense
відповідно мати оці от білдери має сенс
this too this is also similar to the same story
це теж це теж схоже на ту саму історію
that we already have existing abstractions there is an
що в нас вже є існуючі абстракції є
existing structure and adding some new
існуюча структура і додавати якусь нову
structure new abstractions is something that
структуру нові абстракції це те що
is difficult and often do not want to do as
дається тяжко і не хочеться робити часто
a developer
розробника
and the last example we once
і останній приклад ми колись там
got together with friends and discussed a
зібрались з друзями і обговорювали
project on React how to develop it and
проект на реакті як його розроблять і
there was such a problem that we have conditionally
там була така проблема що є у нас умовно
stupid components there some smart
там тупі компоненти якісь розумні
components and there is not enough of some
компоненти і не вистачає якоїсь
abstraction to coordinate more such
абстракції для координації більш таких
high-level actions and I say so
висо високорівневих дій і я кажу так
you can do it just add a controller
можна ж зробити додати просто контролер
but it turns out that because no one in that
але виходить із-за того що в тому
project did that it was
проекті ніхто так не робив то воно було
uncomfortable to add such a new way
некомфортно додавати отакий новий спосіб
new new abstraction which did not
нову нову абстракцію якої до цього не
exist before although in Google Well for example I had to
існувала хоча в Гуглі Ну наприклад треба
implement a certain
було реалізувати мені там певну
subsystem there and I see that I simply
підсистему і я бачу що просто Мені не
lack a number of additional abstractions there on
вистачає там ряда додаткових абстракцій
top of  which will be convenient to work with and
поверх з якими буде зручно працювати і
reuse and which will be able to
перевикористовувати І які зможуть все
hide all the configuration details inside below
всередині сховати деталі конфігурації
low-level abstractions, this is
більш низь низькорівневих абстракцій це
in the interface in ui, I created
в інтерфейсі в ui я створив там
controllers there that really
контролери які прям чудово-чудово
helped and simplified the code and its
допомогли і спростили код і його
support, these are stories. That's
підтримку отакі от історії Отака от
the idea, I hope it was interesting. Write in
думка сподіваюсь було цікаво пишіть в
the comments if you had a similar
коментарях чи у вас було таке схоже
feeling or if you have observed this in
відчуття чи таке ви спостерігали на
any projects and thank you very much to all
якихось проектах і дуже дякую всім
the sponsors for supporting the channel.
спонсорам за підтримку каналу